So yes um the uh the suta for today it's
um sanguta nikaya 35
246 um
um
probably most of most people would have
read it. It's like a famous the simile
of the loot but uh it's really the the
the things that are mentioned in the
sutas before the simile of the loot that
are kind of more interesting well
certainly more relevant for the
practice. Uh the uh because whatever bikuni
Uh the uh because whatever bikuni
regarding forms cognizable by the eye,
should there arise desire or greed or
hate or delusion or even resistance
batiga of their chetaso which is of
their chitta
from that they should reign in the
chitta. So I left chettas and chitta in
pi because
um just to kind of indicate things that
are pertaining to chitta and that are
kind of chitta's doing to put it that
way. Um because with the word mind mind this
Um because with the word mind mind this
mind that mano mind my mind chitta mind
it kind of gets it gets a bit blurred.
And also same it's like with the word
resistance uh patiga because like if you
look at the common translations they
just say aversion.
Oh if there is even a version in my
mind. So again it kind of becomes um the
whole the whole meaning of this very
obviously short like what three lines it
becomes flattened in the sense that you
could see the clearly like the first
paragraph says should there arise desire
or greed or hate i.e. aversion or
delusion or even a patiga. So it's
different than hate. It's different than
aversion. But if you just translate it like oh
But if you just translate it like oh
greed, hate, delusion or even any
aversion, it kind of becomes like a like
a poetic sort of and it completely loses
the depth because it's the piga of their
chetta. So not just oh some slight
aversion cuz somebody didn't put sugar
in my coffee or something. It's a bit
more phenomenological than that and
that's kind of the point of why like
sometimes it's good to leave certain
things completely untransated.
Um so he says basically so yes if any of
these things are found in the chitta
uh stemming from it being pushed forward
by the chitta from that they should
reign in the chitta
by thinking this this path is fearful
with terror with terror with thorns with
thicket a wrong path a bad path
difficult to travel this path of desire,
of greed, of hate or delusion that path.
So this path is frequented by ignorable
asapurisa. It's not the path frequented
by the noble sapurisa. So it doesn't
lead to wisdom. Basically, it's not
worthy of you. So, it's like a generic
stock phrase to describe a type of
reflection that you need to be bringing
in front of your cheetah, in front of
your mind, sustaining it, reminding it
like like relentlessly reminding it of
that. Because again, when the animal
wants to go over the fence, you need to
remind it why it is dangerous to do so.
And if he wants to go over the fence
frequently, well, you frequently have to
remind it. It's not a one and done.
Um,
and then it goes to repeat the same. So,
one should rein the chitter from forms
cognizable by the eye,
uh, sight, sounds, smell, taste,
touches, basically ideas as well. So
when when mental when thoughts mental
phenomena images present themselves
you would see the cheetah wanting to
leap towards them with lust with greed
with hatred.
Um
you have to rein it in like say no and
then remind it of the
drawbacks of the dangers of doing so and
benefits of not doing so.
So it repeats the same this path is
fearful with terror with thorns with
tickets a wrong path a bad path
difficult to travel. So frequented by
ignorable not frequented by the noble
it's not worthy and again why is it not
worthy? Well, anybody who wants to
practice the Buddhist teaching
uh should be aligning, aspiring towards
and working towards alignment with the
values presented by the Buddha because
you yourself see the value in those
values so to speak. Like you see the
value in training, you have faith in it
so that you can be free from suffering.
you have a genuine um profound desire to
be free from dooka, free from liability,
free from attachment, free from any
danger. So it's a real thing. But it's
just like if you forget that
then chitta can pressure you back to
things you know are an obstacle for what
you actually want. It's like that um
what is it?
Tal talaputa. I think it was Tal Buddha
in that um terriata when when he was
talking to his own chitta back when he
was in the forest because uh and saying
basically like oh before I became a monk
when I was a householder my own mind was
telling me hey leave this crowded and
dusty life go forth uh enjoy the freedom
of the wilderness you know practice for
the freedom of suffering so it was quite
inspired basically his own mind was
quite inspired to practice. So then he
did it. He went forth then went to the
forest and now the mind was like well
yeah you know we did this I now I want
something else. So then he wanted to go
back and then he was saying to the mind
like hold on well you were the one that
brought me here
now you want to go back to that which
you yourself said was not worthy and
everything else. So then he's like no no
I'm going to make you sit here now with
me um and we're going to work through
this and you're not going back. And
yeah, he went through it and became an
arant. Um, so it says like, oh, suppose because
Um, so it says like, oh, suppose because
there was a rich crop, the crop guardian
is negligent and a crop eating ox having
entered that crop would indulge himself
in intoxication and negligence as much
as he wants. Even so, because an
uninstructed whirling um assutting
without restraint in the six bases of
pressure, Pasa I I translated as pressure. Well,
Pasa I I translated as pressure. Well,
most of you already know that uh
indulges in intoxication and negligence
as much as he wants in the five strands
of sensual pleasure.
So it's kind of
even pertains to somebody who say
um who's just at the very beginning of
the practice which would be the theuta
the uninstructed warling who might have
started learning some instruction
um so allowing
the mind the chitta to uh enter the crop
indulge indulge itself in the crop as
much as it wants with intoxication and
negligence towards the sensuality, the
five strands of sensual pleasure.
Uh, equals what the previous paragraph
just described. Equal equals following
the ignorable path that takes away from
wisdom that obstructs the wisdom and
does not lead to freedom from suffering.
It's kind of pretty self-evident really.
But doesn't matter how self-evident it
is when the pressure is there to to act
out of the greed desire and so on. Uh
the context is lost. So as I said that's
all like you have to remind yourself of
what you actually want what you actually
value and then re in the mind and that
the principle of that training is like
from up to the aranchip that's the part that
up to the aranchip that's the part that
doesn't change whatsoever.
Um
so then the next um let me just scroll
this up. Yeah.
So then the next paragraph is the
opposite. Suppose because there was a
rich crop crop guardian is diligent crop
eating ox um enters that crop. But then
the crop guardian would take him firmly
by the nose. Having taken firmly by the
nose he would pin him down firmly by the
neck. having pinned him down firmly by
the neck, he would strike him well with
a stick. H having struck him well with a
stick, he would let him go. In other
words, teach him a lesson. Like, no, you
don't go there. Like, we've been through
this before. We rationalize many times.
Both you and I know that that this is
the the ignorable path, the obstruction.
It's just there's no more discussion. In
other words, it's just like grab you by
the nose and pull you back.
So and then even even the suit describes
and then second time the ox does it then
the third time then the 103rd time does
it you repeat the same no you are not
going there I'm not fueling neither that
attitude nor that behavior you can kick
and scream as much as you want like a
spoiled brat if you give in you convey
the wrong message and by giving in I
mean that literally choose to go down
that path it's not like oh giving in u
doesn't mean having your mind uh having
your mind have a desire. That's not you
giving in
uh your mind getting angry, cheetah
getting angry, that's not you giving in
but you choosing to allow it to act you
to act on account of it that is you
giving in. So that's why you don't need
to as I said strangle or kill your mind
or not perceive anything to be free from
it. you just not be the one you just not
u you must not be the one who would be
making the choice of yeah okay go ahead
into the crop.
So the problem is not that the animal
wants to go back to the crop and eat as
much as it wants and so on. The problem
is that you keep letting it. That's it.
And that's that line of the restraint
like you don't need to torment yourself.
You don't need to sleep on the bed of
nails and stuff like that to just
somehow magically cure cure the mind
from the eyes. like no, you just need to
be uh to recognize that you must not be
the one willingly, consciously making
the choice that affirms sensuality,
greed, aversion, distraction and so on.
That's the middle path. So you recognize
that then then the practice will not
necessarily be unpleasant
because again like you have the mind
comes like this. The mind sometimes
comes up like that.
This is the line I won't cross.
Everything else outside of the line is
not my problem. So it's like a lot of
burden comes down from you.
So then it compares this bringing back
to the of the ox compares the Buddha
compares that to a monk taming his
cheetah. So even so the paragraph says bikus when
So even so the paragraph says bikus when
a biku when for a biku a cheetah is
tamed well tamed regarding the six basis
of pressure in other words the six types
of crops well the animal learned its
lesson you're not letting it go there
you bring it back you present it with
perceptions and you're diligent in that
regard you don't go around complaining
you don't go around complaining
um feeling sorry for yourself because
your mind still wants these things cuz
again it's like literally comp
complaining that well the dog still
wants to go and chew the bone. Well,
yeah, what a surprise.
Still wants to go and chase other
animals. Yeah, what a surprise. That's
what the animal does. That's what Chitta
does. So, it's like, no, that's not my
So, it's like, no, that's not my
problem. My problem is if I'm the one
opening the gate and then paying the
price for it. So, I'll stop doing that
and the animal will come up. How long it
takes to calm down? Well, we'll just
have to see once that happens.
So it says even so because when for au
the chitta is tamed well tamed regarding
the six bases of pressure six types of
crops it remains centered within
it settles down it becomes unified it
enters samadei.
So when the mind is stained, when chitta
is stained in regard to the six bases of
contact, how well the Buddha just described in
how well the Buddha just described in
the same sense how a shepherd would use
a stick to prevent the ox from going
into the wrong crops. That is how
it can't be any clearer than that
really. Even the simile is not
technical. Then the mind settles down and becomes
Then the mind settles down and becomes
unified. Then you enter samadi. then you
develop samadei.
So if there is no samadei, it's cuz
there is no right training in regard to
the crop. There is still let allowing
the oxen to go into the crop as much as
you want despite what you might be
telling yourself or what you might be
believing.
And then he goes into kind of the the
the second half giving a simile in
regarding to the um the loot and the
king. So suppose because the sound of a loot
So suppose because the sound of a loot
was never heard before by a king or or
or a royal minister.
He might hear a sound of the loot and
say, "Good man, whose sound is this so
enchanting, so desirable, so
intoxicating, so infatuating, so
captivating?" They would say to him,
"Well, this sir is the that which is
called the loot. The sound of which is
so enchanting and captivating."
Um, he would then say, "Go man, bring me
that loot." They would bring him the
loot. And he would say, "Enough of it.
Bring me just the sound."
Then they would explain to him that this
loot is made of many components of great
components. It speaks it speaks having
dependent on many components depending
on the parchment, the belly, the arm,
the bridge, the strings, the plerum.
depending on the appropriate effort of a
person. Thus this loot sir is or sire is made of
Thus this loot sir is or sire is made of
many components each peaks having
dependent on many components.
Then the man the king would choose to
split the loot into 10 or 100 pieces.
Having split it, he would splinter it.
Having splintered it, he would burn it
with fire and make it into ashes. Having
made it into ashes, he would winnow it
in a strong wind and let it be carried
away by a swift flowing river.
He would say a poor thing indeed is this
so-called loot. Whatever a loot may be
herein the people are excessively
negligent and deceived. Meaning he
destroyed the loot trying to get to the
sound and there was no sound.
So he couldn't find the sound. We we'll
get to that part with when we do the
questions later as to why this is
relevant to the first part.
So it says even so because investigates
form as far as a design designation or
destination of form goes he investigates
feeling he investigates perception he
investigates determinations he
investigates um consciousness yes
um consciousness yes
um as he investigates form feeling
perception termination consciousness as
far the destination of consciousness
goes whatever there was of I am of mine
that for him is no more
So,
so yeah, um that whole kind of the
second part is just to to illustrate,
let's say it's like an inside view
of the desire that you're taming through
practicing the first part of the suta,
which is bringing the oxen back from the
crop. Bringing the oxen back from the
crop. Uh so the the a few questions that um
Uh so the the a few questions that um
that I compiled um
that kind of sort of try to bridge the
theory and the practice between this uh
in this suta was the the question of the
the leaking fence or the not properly
closed gate or whatever similar
comparison you want to use. So in the
similar of the ox the guardian only
strikes the ox when it enters the crop.
So you don't go around beating it all
the time if it's not doing anything
wrong. What is wrong in this context?
Well, the suta clearly describes it.
Sensual desire is wrong, greed is wrong,
um hatred, anger is wrong and so on.
So
in in one's daily life,
can you discern your chitta
as something that's already leaning
towards those things? In other words,
can you notice when the animal is
already inclining or planning to try and sneak
inclining or planning to try and sneak
through the gate?
or do you only see it when it's right
there and you're trying to like drag it
back from the wrong crop?
Because that's the important factor.
It's like if you're waiting for the bull
to be entering the crop to start paying
attention, it's too late. Usually, it's
too late. So, you need to start noticing
the tendencies
of your mind
way before it comes into like a
fullblown, oh, now I just have to be beating it
oh, now I just have to be beating it
with a stick and pulling it by the nose
and it's really hard cuz it weighs a
ton. So that's like um
So that's like um
obviously it's like a very important
consideration, but it's also something
as I said it's like you have to
it's going to have layers to it. In
other words, you know, you might think
you're noticing the um the um the
background state of the animal. Oh, is
my mind leaning and so on. But you can
know whether you are say correctly or
accurately enough doing that noticing if
when the animal is at the doorstep of
the crop.
Uh
are you able to actually pull it back?
Are you able to to not let it go that
way? Or are you like, "Okay, we're just
Or are you like, "Okay, we're just
eating the crop now and then I'll start
again later." If if if that's the case,
if if that's the case more often than
not means you are not noticing the state
of the animal early enough. So you got
to start you got to stop distracting
yourself with other seemingly important
things and look backwards uh peripheral
at the background of your mind. what
kind of
um
sort of like moods, inclinations are
there leaning, shaping up like what kind
of clouds are coming up the horizon way
before you are hit by a storm.
Um because that is the reason why why
the animal is still able why you're not
able to pull the animal out of the crop.
Basically, it's just it's too late.
So then the like the second question is
about the suta describing the whole um
path of following desire or aversion
either way desire as um sensual desire
aversion as ill will hatred acting out
it's all on the same plane pertains to
like the world so to speak. So the suta
describes it as the path um which is
like path covered with thorns
dangerous path where you're just going
to injure yourself.
So that's this the question is like when
the um when that patiga that as I said
the natural the fundamental the
underlying resistance toward your own
senses well resistance or chitta towards
your own senses to be technical
um so whether it's just a neutral
it's still resistance by the way so it
cannot be entirely neutral but what what
what I'm saying there is not necessarily
aversion it's not necessarily hate
hatred or real will. It's where hatred
or real will finds its basis from
same in the same sense how uh a sign of
suba the sign of beautiful agreeable
shape form sound doesn't matter. It's
not where sensuality is but it's where
sensuality finds its base from.
So whether it's as subtle as that
neutral that you just that resistance
that you just have towards pretty much
your own physicality naturally because
senses are a burden they offer inertia
that inertia is patiga well but whether
that becomes your own aversion that's a
secondary thing. So the question here
it's like how far can you go back and
notice the precursors to your desire or
ill will the the the clouds that coming
up the horizon
or do you need to like have them right
in front of your face to become aware of
them? If so it's because most likely
you're probably distracting yourself too
much with other things and not investing
enough time to contemplate. sit quietly
with this and think it like you know
invoke it, remember it, recollect it,
try to clarify it and so on and then see
it, apply their life so to speak like
okay so what is the current the widest
possible horizon of my current mood?
What is it?
Because that whole like a like a horizon
I think I remember it was and
discussing it in the early letters. It
was like um they were describing
relationship if I remember correctly
between chitta and chetana as like a
horizon and things arising from that
horizon. So it's like a sets up the
direction and then things arise from
there. So that's why it's it's like it's
So that's why it's it's like it's
important for for that phenomenon to be
to well to not be as theoretical for
people but to actually you start to
relate to it in your own practical like
uh experience day-to-day experience as a
whole because it is there all these
moods and precursors and wide kind of as
I said very very peripheral leaning and
preferences are there and they are
leaning you and and setting you up uh
for what to follow out of them. So that
the sooner you spot them there,
obviously the less kind of physical
effort you will have to uh apply onto
the the bull to pull him back. Yeah. So um
So um
so yeah, now the like the whole simile
of the loot uh sister mentioned in her
in her reply before it's like a simile u
compared it to a rainbow which I think
is quite a good simile. Like the king
wants the sound of the loot but ignores
the the the existing presently
simultaneously existing unity of its
parts. Because you can have the strings,
you can have the body, you could have
the the uh the musician, but if you have
them separate, not unified in that
particular arrangement, you will not
have the sound of the loot. And it's the
same exact same with the with the
rainbow like the water droplets, the
sun, your point of view, the angle is
the necessary simultaneously present
factors for the uh phenomenon of rainbow
to be seen. Now does that mean rainbow
is not real as such? Does that mean
sound of the loot is not real as such?
No, not at all. That would be a lazy way
out saying oh because you can take it
apart it doesn't exist in some sort of
imagin imaginable reality but that's
just basic kind of contradiction in
terms and it's quite an irrational
standpoint which is of why mysticism
comes out of it. No it is really such
nobody denies that the loot has a
pleasant sound
but the sound it's not found in any of
the specific components.
Nobody denies that I am factually seeing
the rainbow. I mean, I can describe the
colors. I can even describe the size.
Oh, there's a double one. Look. So, it's
like, so what is that not real? No, it's
real. But obviously, if I look for it
where it isn't, it it's not going to be
there. So, why is this relevant? Well,
desire is the same. Ill will is the
same. Pretty
Pretty
much any pressure that Chitta exerts in
you, it's the same nature. See, you see
the rainbow, the experience of it, the
natural pressure of unenlightened mind
is to push you towards it. But towards
what? It's there when you are not closer
or too close to it so to speak or when
you're not too far. So it's there the
way it is there. But the tendency of the
mind is to push you forward to push you
for more of it and you don't know where
to look for more of it. So where do you
look? Well, you look among the sense
object you look among the forms the uh
the feeling the all the other uh
palpable things. That's why after the
similar of the loot the Buddha start
describing the aggregates how when the
monk starts looking the aggregates you
won't find the sense of I am there
because the sense of I am shares the
same nature.
But on a more well on a more practical
level for somebody say who is kind of
still working on on that uh training the
ox you could see exactly the same
principle revealed in just a central
desire and I'm pretty sure like
everybody with any well with some degree
of self-awareness but say outside of the
context of the Buddhist practice outside
of the the sutas
deep down has a recognition because it
has happened so many times You have a
desire towards something. You have that
pressure towards something perceived
currently as a as a kind of dependent on
the the unified components of your
experience to put it that way on sides
uh eyes desire this and that. So it's
like that that kind of pressure it's
really as such to that extent. But then
what would people naturally do? Well
then they would go for more of the sites
more of this. But they themselves would
then experience that oh well this was a
bit of a letdown
because you don't find it there. You
don't find those things there. Same with
the food.
Like it's that
pretty much joy of anticipation
is where your happiness what your
happiness is bound with. Once you start
eating or consuming or doing this, you
you went too far
and you just find yourself, okay, desire
is gone because the phenomenon of
rainbow is gone cuz I went too far. The
angle changed. There are no more water
droplets there or whatever.
And that's why each time it sets you up
from the beginning, so to speak, to fail
in exactly the same way
because you're looking for it where it
can't be found.
And now the same principle of just the
basic core sensual desire that always
sets you towards sense objects. But as I
was saying that long time ago in those
talks from Sri Lanka, it's like
a mere thought of seeing or touching or
tasting something already produces like
excitement, anticipation, desire,
pressure even more. But it's like but
hold on. If through a common assut
belief pleasure is in touching, tasting,
seeing, smelling, listening and so on,
how can you already experience the
pleasure way before you are in contact
with those things?
Way before you even went and kind of
sought it and found it and looked at it
and ate it and so on. Yet, you're
experiencing the same. So, it's like if
it's truly in those things, you could
only experience it when you're actively
in contact with them.
But that's the point. It was never in
those things. So the more you are
ignoring the um the whole necessity of
restraint, necessity of training in
virtue, necessity of withdrawing the ox,
uh the more you are reinforcing the
belief that as I said even when he's
honest with himself knows that yeah
things are not really satisfying at the
end of the day
like doesn't matter how much but I
forget about that and then I continue to
kind of uh uh distract myself with the
thrill of the chase.
So it's like chasing the the rainbows.
Well, I know I can't find them. But
anyway, I I ignore that part because
again, the activation is what gives me
joy. So that's why this similar is relevant
So that's why this similar is relevant
relevant to the whole restraint and
everything. So it's like in the in the
beginning, yes, you have to just whack
the bull and pull it back and not let it
go there, but eventually you you have to
start seeing through the whole pattern.
And it's like hold on yes there is
pressure but how many times like even
before the restraint and after restraint
I know it's not in those things. Now my
chitta needs to know that. So that's why
these perceptions of the danger and so
on so that the same knowledge
the obviousness of it will sink to to
the mind down to the mind and when it
does so you don't have to be uh pulling
the oxin back. it it won't go there
because it it there was nothing there to
find to from the beginning. What he
thought he was getting from those
things, it wasn't there. And that was
the sole problem. There was a sole
deception of sensuality and stuff. All
the similarities that the Buddha talked
about like if it if it were not a
deception, it would not have been unh
wholesome. And that's actually another
sut, isn't it? Where the Buddha says
mara or or sorry, hunter does not set up
a trap for the welfare of of the animal.
is just cannot be done for that purpose.
So a hunter does not set up a trap
because he sets up the trap to get the
animal to get the meat to hunt you down.
So it's like so you can't go around, you
can't see a hunter, but imagine yourself
entering a forest and you see something
that really looks like a trap.
It's like, hm, this looks like it's
trying to get me to go there for
whatever reason.
a man with like normal rational mind and
a normal as I said common sense wisdom
would such a man choose to go there or
was like no no I I I probably wouldn't
like why would I like the way like if
something needs to be set up to get you
there first
it's something you naturally wouldn't
trust and that's exactly how sensuality
is set up
is set up to get you there first and
Then the place like but hold on. If I'm
already feeling the pressure before I
even got there means that's already a
setup that has nothing to do with things
I'm trying to get to.
So why would I go there? It can't be for
my welfare. If somebody set this up in
this manner, it cannot be for my welfare
because it's deceitful.
And that's one of the dangers of all the
other implications that you trapped
yourself in.
As the suta says, the ox eventually
stops entering the crop because it well
it learned from the stick. It learned
from your relentless recollection of the
right perception sustaining the context
at the right time. As I said, you don't
have to go around reciting the danger of
sensuality 24/7 as some sort of mantra.
No. But when you recognize that you are
being pressured towards choosing
sensuality or ill will, that's when you
bring up those context. No exception, no
slacking. If the mind doesn't come up
with it, great. Put your feet up and
relax. So the question here was like do you
So the question here was like do you
like do you do these such reflections?
Do you do you remember yourself like
times in the past when you allowed
sensuality when you acted out of ill
will and so on? Um well was it pleasant?
Was it beneficial? Who was the main
benefactor of it? You or the wild animal
that get you to do it?
It's like so recognizing those those
implicitly kind of unpleasant ways. Do
do you recollect that as well the
emotional side of those things to make
it as I said more more pertinent of a
reflection rather than just
theoretically as I said recite through
the danger actually feel the danger in
other words
feel the drawbacks
so make the connection make the
connection between the drawbacks of
things that followed see you could say
like oh I don't see a connection between
like giving and then something that's
happening it's like yeah but something
else that can happen unfavorable. They
can happen and you know your mind will
kick and scream and suffer and try and
bite you as a result and you would
suffer. Well, that is because that mind
is untrained. Why is that mind
untrained? Well, because you've been
allowing it into sensuality and into
your will carelessly. So, there is a
connection.
You just need to not forget it. And when
you forget it, you need to remember it.
need to clarify it and protect it so
that next time thereity you see all the
other collateral damage implied in it
so to speak.
So yeah and then the in the end the
presence of the I am of I am that was as
I said the if you follow the same
principle of the the the rainbow existing real as
of the the the rainbow existing real as
such or the sound of the loot being real
as such yet dependent on things that are
not it that are defining it. Uh it's the
same with the presence of I am. So the
presence of I am is real as such. Your
sense of whoever you are is real as
such. It's not an illusion. It's not an
anata. Nothing is real. Nothing is mine.
No, it's real as such. It's just a
mistaken identity.
You think of it more than it actually
is. To put it that way. You think
rainbow is over there, you know, 350 m
away in those molecules. And if I go
there and get it, I'll I I'll I'll find
it. I'll have it. You King thought the
sound of the loot was in the strings.
So, he started dissecting it and taking
it apart.
So, it's like that's why again, you
can't dissect your own aggregates. I
mean you can try
but the result would be absolutely
destroyed loot and now without any
capacity for the sound or understanding
of the relationship between the two. So
the when the Buddha says you examine the
form and stuff you examine the nature of
the form as that which kind of enables
the sense of I am to depend on it
and you just you go you don't need to go
further than that you don't need to
start tormenting torturing destroying
your torturing destroying your form your
feelings and so on your consciousness I
mean I don't know how you would do that
but people might try in order to prove
yourself that that a sense of I am is
not yours no you just You need to
basically stop thinking of yourself as
independent of form, feeling,
perception, determination, and
consciousness. Literally, that's it.
Stop regarding yourself as the owner.
Contemplate the impermanence to
undermine the safety, the the emotional
safety of the sense of ownership. Not
just to like as I said fall into a
theoretical view that everything is
constantly changing therefore nothing is
really mine therefore everything is an
ata therefore the Buddha was right. It's
like no no no if you truly develop anata
well you'll be free from suffering. So
the the the contemplation the
dissections the analysis that the sutas
describe it's not mindless scientific uh
scholarly analysis of random components
like how Abidama or commentaries do it.
It's the actual contemplation of the
live situation
being undermined by something else
that's there. So, it's like, oh, I'm
hearing the sound of the loot, but I'm
not forgetting that it depends on these
quite irrelevant
uh emotionally insignificant or even
disgusting parts in and of themselves.
That's why you know the contemplation of
the body and the dangers and so on that
other sutas talk about it's to just lose
the desire towards the sound of the
loot. lose the enchantment and and and
ridiculous idea of chasing the rainbow
or become uninticated with your own
sense of I am with your own sense of
self self view sense of I am conceited
and everything else by undermining it
rightly uh through recognition of things that do
uh through recognition of things that do
actually determine it that is
inseparable from and depends on so
that's that's it that's the sole purpose
of this so one is the the difference
between aversion and patiga. Um they're
all talks
that talk about it more so I don't want
to be going into it. Um
but um I think I already covered it
didn't I? So
think of the resistance basically just a
say there is you're feeling neutral. Say
you're feeling neutral. So there's like
nothing nothing like bothering you or or
overtly pressuring you. So there's no
aversion, there's no desire currently at
least. So you're just sitting as I said
there is a natural inertia of your
existence as a whole. There is a natural
weight. You know the body, the blob that
you have to carry, the the the the
situation, the
the heat, the cold, just just all the
little things are felt through a degree
of their own like resistance, a degree
of that lit like in physics, inertia.
That's it. It's a it's a good word. And
again I think we were
talking about translating rupa as as
inertia as that which which offers
inertia. That's how you know it's there.
So that's the natural part. When I say
patiga that in and of itself it's a bit
as I said
weighty so to speak it has some weight
on when that's not seen through that is
the basis.
Well, it's kind of the basis for even
sensuality when you think about it.
It's certainly basis for aversion, but
it's basis for sensuality as well
because it's if it's not seen through,
you will be discontent with it. And
discontent as one of the Marad's
daughters goes hand inhand with
sensuality because when you are
discontent you will then be seeking well
the only means of escape from that that
you know which is sensual pleasures
which is falling back into the belief
that if I follow the rainbow I'll get to
the the source the core the the
substance the the the the center of it
and uh and then you just as I said
deceive yourself with that repetitive
ride. But yeah, that patiga is the base
for it. And that's actually that suta.
Well, I can't remember the I don't
remember the numbers anymore, but uh I
do remember it was the um
Arita. Yeah. When he said uh when they
would ask like, "Oh, who does the
mindfulness of breathing here and how
you do it?" And Arita said, "I'm doing
it." Says, "How?" I was like, "Well,
mindfully I breathe in, mindfully I
breathe out." uh I know breath is there
or something like that and he said uh
having abandoned desire for sense
pleasures of the past uh having
abandoned for the sense pleasures of the
future and the present obviously I'm abiding
and the present obviously I'm abiding
now uh free from internal patiga like
not obviously seeing through the
internal patiga there is no more desire
for any forms of pleasure even the ones
that I used to experience and the Buddha
said yep that is one way of doing anopan
but it's not complete and then went well
the suta goes into the stock phrase of
like repeating the other like you know I
will breed in like this I'll breathe in
like that
kind of showing that there probably
there will be more nuances but I don't
think that the sutras necessarily have
preserved those nuances of descriptions
which is obviously a shame but nothing
we can do about it uh but pointing out
that okay yeah great now do it even more
and kind of um completely approved the
sense of I am that would be the result
of fulfilling the anapanasati done
rightly the right recollection but as
Arita explained it was like the way he
was describing it you could see like aha
seeing through patiga internally being
free from it by seeing through it he has
no desire towards sensual pleasures
which is exactly how it work if if your
own presence neutral presence of your
own senses the weight the inertia is not
bothersome to the chitta let alone you.
Your own animal does not mind him. Well,
you would feel fairly light,
um fairly unbburdened,
uh fairly freed,
uh and yeah, and that would be
physically felt. That's kind of the the
the funny irony of it.
Uh but again, you won't be able to deal
with that pertigga if you're still
having acting out of sensuality,
uh sexuality, coarse sensuality, um ill
will and so on. It's like this this this
is way too buried by those acts that are
obviously rooted in it.
And then the um the second uh question
was
the way to explain to the chitta that um
aversion or sensuality is like a thorn
is well one of the ways he says I
suppose to contemplate the benefit of
the peaceful neutral feeling. Well, yes,
if you would if you contemplate the
danger of the of following those
pressures first.
Um, so how to do this practically? Well,
that's how you do it practically. Like
if practically
contemplating benefits of the neutral
feeling and not quite doing it for the
chitta is not listening to you, well
then you have to practically contemplate
the dangers of it. Something a bit a bit
heavier. Uh, and when that kind of
scares it back, then you show it what's
actually a see. When you don't go there,
this is what you get. And this is
actually beneficial. But if you're
trying to show to a raging animal that
staying calm is peaceful, it's it's not
going to see it. So, you can't really
force the the contemplation of the
neutral feeling.
uh it needs to be in the piece of it
needs to be discerned and recognized on
account of not following the pleasure
the pressure that comes out of the the
craving towards more pleasure the
craving to to get rid of the aversion
and pain and so on and not acting out of
those things. So that that that is the
only practical uh method that you can
really do. Seems it seems to me that
when I do allow the cow to eat from the
crop that isn't supposed to the line
between me and the cow is blurred.
Is that because appropriation arises
with all the language increases sense of
am? Well, yeah. But see the answer is
really not relevant
in a sense. It doesn't matter why it
happens. You know exactly why it
happens. It happened because the choice
you made allowed it to go there. So stop
doing that. You don't have to worry
about appropriation and how it comes and
why it works and and why and how it
works and so on.
So it happens because well you lost
perspective. The the shepherd that was
supposed to keep the bull back didn't
and then lost perspective and so what do
you do on account of it? It's like do
you wake up
acknowledge it acknowledge the
implications of it the weight of the
mistake in order to help you to you know
not fall back to it into it so easily as
before? Or does the shepherd then
pretend okay well let's pretend this
never happened won't happen again next
time I'll make a harder determination
and magically believe and concentrate
harder and go on a longer retreat and
hopefully mind won't go there it's like
no no then the mind doesn't understand
any of your token gestures
any of your observances
um determinations
and things that you magically are kind
of trying to hoping they will transfer
the the the the right perceptions down
to the animal and they will just stop
wanting those things. No, it's like the
sut is very clear.
You know what the crop is. If you don't
know, well, you learn what a crop is.
You learn where the outlines of it are.
You cannot not be aware of the choice as
I said and that is that's a good thing
because if the problem were truly
the fact that animal can still have a
desire or real will well aranchi would
never be possible because you have no
say in that
and again that's what uh contemporarily
generally people would think if I try
hard enough determine hard enough
country hard enough these things will
just just just disappear
because they were always the problems
like no
the animal pressuring you to to to to go
well the animal trying to go to the to
the crop
that's just what animal does you
recognizing that and tolerating it
that's the doorway that's the problem
that's the crossroad that's a mistake
that's the obstruction
and that's why aranchip is possible
because you stop doing it you stop
fueling it you stop reinforcing it
through the As I said uh ignorant choice
animal will calm down. I mean countless
sutras describe that through training in
virtue you develop samadei. You develop
internal actual peace effortless peace
not peace dependent on the circumstances
and uh right retreat conditions or right
inspiration or something. No peace on
account of the animal not wanting those
crops anymore. genuine safety
like the simile of the you know the the
relay chariots as well that's always
what comes to mind
it's like it will a purification of
virtue I training the oxen leads to the
purification of um of the of the mind
leads to samadei which then leads to the
purification of the views
and that's exactly what I said like the
questioning now why does appropriation
happen it's like questioning the views
while the crop you know is still not
guarded. But if you guard the crop animal
But if you guard the crop animal
actually calms down you see through that
they you will understand appropriation.
The views will be purified on account of
that and same works with the right view. It's
and same works with the right view. It's
not a it's not a it's not a magic bullet
that just hits you out of nowhere.
It's like you start taming as the suta
says does this because he's a suta. If
does this because he's a suta. If
somebody's suta and learns he'll stop
doing he stop allowing the oxen to go
into sensuality to act out of ill will.
He'll start training it because he
learned he starts training it because he
learned the oxin will come down. He'll
get to see it and then he get to
recognize that this sense of I am is
dependent on the existing components of
this simultaneously existing experience
as a whole or aggregates or whatever you
want to describe it and he will be
unable to now hold on to it as the
center of experience as mine or find
safety in it. He will be free from
atavada follows the same principle. He will be
follows the same principle. He will be
free from the sense of I am.
That's it.
But again it need that those connections
those perceptions need to be made
through diligent effort by you because
well probably not any of you but I think
generally like a wider audience uh you
can't really blame people for it but
like when you hear this I think many
people would just then aha okay so I'll
just keep the precepts
because obviously listen I listened to
this talk for two hours and clearly
precepts are very important so I'll just
keep the precepts with implicit belief
that now everything will fall into place
because I adopted the new set of
external observances.
But internally a person remains still
not making connections, not drawing
right perceptions, not drawing right
associations, not showing right things
to the animal when when when it
pressures you and just okay no no. It's
like well you do have a basis. You did
get the first chariot of virtue, but
you're not really moving it. So you're
not getting any closer to the actual
samadei because you're doing it blindly.
So you need to learn for about a virtue
and about the precepts so that you can
understand the principles behind that
training and the principles behind that
training is obviously what we spoke so
many times in so many other talks
watching for your intentions not just
well the rule says this I don't do it
and I don't think about it
like but if there is no rule I mean
there were no rules in the beginning
literally imagine that
the Buddha just told the dharma And
everybody who heard it, who understood
it, knew what to do.
Does that mean killing was allowed?
Sexual intercourse was allowed?
Lying was allowed?
Well, it wasn't stated that it wasn't
allowed. How do they know?
How do they know?
So ask yourself,
do I know why those things are well
later were defined as not allowed? In
other words, do I know why those things
are an obstacle or am I just keeping the
precepts cuz well I was told to do so
and I have faith in that. I find it
inspiring. But no, no, no. Do I know for
myself the principle
the principle
why sexuality is an obstruction to
seeing the dharma, fulfilling the
dharma? Why acting out of ill will is a
obstruction to seeing the dharma, to
fulfilling the dharma.
Why as I said the wrong speech, gossip,
lying, um
comfort, beautifification, why are those
things actual obstacle towards
fulfilling the dharma?
Because if you don't know, well, that's
your priority really. That's why your
virtue is not leading to samadi, which
is not leading to the right view.
cuz you you stopped the chariot. You you
you took it for granted. You you thought
getting the chariot of virtue is all I
need. I got the car. It's right there in
my driveway.
But I'm not going with it in the right
direction basically.
Uh Bante, you often say that while
appropriation goes away, the sense of
self remains. It's not just mine
anymore. If I, my and I am all go away,
what in the suta terms is the thing
remaining that feels like the sense of
self? Um, so yeah, see the problem with
this question is that assumes Putin's
point of view and Arhan's point of view
at the same time and expects an answer
that can satisfy both.
And if I give you an answer that can
satisfy both, that won't be the dharma
because it's not open. It won't be
leading onwards towards the practice. It
will be an irrelevant theoretical
information that might be some correct
on the paper but it completely kills the
practice because it led you to believe
that now you know what that is while you
don't put cannot know what an arant is
unless he's on the way of becoming one.
So what remains is what you will see if
you follow what the suta says
when I speak about uh the sense of self
remains I speak about it practically for
those that still have sense of self cuz
usually that is my audience those that
don't they don't need to listen to me
and it's more beneficial practically to
not fall into the view oh yeah the
modern science is proven nothing is
everything is constantly changing
therefore everything is anata The Buddha
was right and so on. Myself is not real.
It is real. The rainbow is real.
Sound of the loot is real.
So when you say it's not mine, do you
regard it as not real or do you regard
it as real? Just not mine. There's a
there's a huge difference there
because more often than not, it's like,
oh, not mine. Not real. Dismissed.
But if you're dismissing it, basically
you're you're ignoring the problem. So I
say no, it is yours.
First technology that is yours. So that
you can see the thing that is yours. See
it for what it is. The ambiguous rainbow
that's not material. I can't find it in
anything more palpable.
It's that tendency to find more palpable
things. It's pretty much why every
puta's effort will fall onto one wrong
view or the other. So learning to see
the rainbow, learning to hear the sound
of the loot correctly means uh undoing
that gratuitous dependence on
probability being the measure of
realness. Because for as long as that is
the state of one's mind, your own
feelings won't be regarded as real. Your
own thoughts won't be regarded as real.
So it is real. It's yours. Take it up.
And then Oh, hold on. This which is mine
does not quite obey my will.
Oh, so it is real. You just showed me
that it has its own inertia.
It depends on things that are completely
not in my control. Equally real.
Yeah, I can say it's mine, but is it
really mine? It becomes obvious to you
that it's not mine. that it cannot be
yours even if you want it to and that's
all that's an art
like you don't need to go further than
that you you obviously you need to
sustain this protect it and develop it
in that sense but you don't need more
answers and permutations and so on
because your sense of self whatever it is well
your sense of self whatever it is well
first for most people it's not even seen
you need to see it real as such you need
to see the rainbow real as such
You need to see the sound of the loot
real as such. Neither here nor there.
That's kind of the point, isn't it? Like
wherever you look for the sound of the
loot, it won't be there. Yet, it's
there. It's there when all these there
are there, but it's not in any
individual one of them. Same with the
rainbow. It's neither here nor there.
Sense of I am, sense of self, even your
own as coarse as it can be. It's neither
here nor there.
But it is real as such. So stop seeking
it on the level of palpability and
recognize it real as such as that which
is neither here nor there. How do I
know? Well, ask yourself a question. Do
I have a sense of I am? Do I have a
sense of whatever whoever whoever I am?
Say your name. You do have a sense. When
you look for where that sense is, you're
not going to find it. And as I said
default kind of direction that he will fall into
kind of direction that he will fall into
is ah therefore it's not real because
the mind does well he himself does not
see any any phenomenological nuances in
between. So if I can't see it, smell it, taste
So if I can't see it, smell it, taste
it, touch it, it's not real.
And you know people would live their
whole life like that thinking their own
thoughts are not really real. their own
intentions that make them smell, taste,
hear and touch are not real.
So that's like what what you need to
what needs to be recognized and that's
that's what I mean like the question is
kind of assumes the validity of the
position that pertains to the beginning
and the end of the internal path and
providing an answer to that will not be
the dharma
because you satisfy both seemingly but
in reality you can't do that. You are
either on one side or you're trailing
towards the other side.
So what is left there? Well, find out by
traveling there yourself.
And you travel there yourself by not
denying what you have now. By learning
how not to own it through undermining
its ownership. Well, through undermining
your ownership of it and certainly not
through denying it or dismissing it.
You often emphasize not practicing a
suba as a way to get rid of the pressure
in terms of the simile. Could we say
it's important to pin down the ox endure
the pressure before the beating
perception of a suba? Uh yes. Well well
it depends how you what what you mean
like if in in your example uh pinning
the ox is enduring the pressure and
beating is the perception of a suba then
yeah sure. But for somebody uh pinning
down the ox might be the assuba and
beating it is the enduring. I don't
know. Um the point is uh yeah like if
say you see the clouds coming up from
the horizon
before the pressure is fully developed
then yeah you should definitely do a
suba that's where it's the suba is done.
That's where the where it can pertain to
the mind rightly. But if you are now
a midst of trying to hold back the bull
and failing the bull is too strong and
you want the whole thing just to end and
you're doing a sububa. Yeah, that's the
general assuba. That's how people do it.
State of mind came up. I must get rid of
it cuz I cannot contain it.
And why I cannot contain it? Well, I
already said that because I haven't
looked at the horizon at all. I haven't
paid attention to it. I haven't
discerned its inclinations,
preferences growing. So yeah, now it's
too late.
So that's something like people do a
suba to get rid of the mind with their
mind states
because they don't see a difference.